A Guide to the Lewis F. Powell Jr. Papers, 1929-1998
Washington and Lee University, School of Law, Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives
- Civic Activities 1946-1971
  - Virginia State Board of Education 1961-1969
    - Subject Files
      - Agenda, 1964, 1968 (Box-folder 254/5)
      - Citizen Education Project, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 254/6-9)
        Includes correspondence, subject files and printed materials.
      - Committee On Raising the Level of Public Education in Virginia, 1966 (Box-folder 254/10)
      - Committees, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 254/11-12)
      - Educational Research, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 254/12)
      - Educational Television, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 254/13)
      - Minutes, 1960-1968 (Box-folder 254/14-25)
      - Policies, 1960-1962 (Box-folder 254/26)
      - Prince Edward County School Board Suit, 1961-1964 (Box-folder 254/27)
      - Reports
        - General, 1960-1967 (Box-folder 254/28-31, Box-folder 255/1)
        - re Legislation Affecting Education, 1959-1968 (Box-folder 255/2)
      - Summer Institutes, 1960-1962 (Box-folder 255/3)
    - Printed Materials, 1960-1970 (Box-folder 255/4)
    - Clippings, 1961-1965 (Box-folder 255/5-7)
  - Virginia Magna Carta Commission 1964-1965 (Box-folder 255/8-16)
    2.5 inches of chronologically arranged correspondence about Powell's service on this body which helped plan and carry out a 750th anniversary celebration at the College of William & Mary in May 1965. Powell gave a speech at this event. Though there is overlap in the documentation, this event is not to be confused with the 750th anniversary celebration of Magna Carta which took place in England a month later. Powell attended that event as President of the ABA and also spoke on that occasion. Documentation of this later event and speech are located in the American Bar Association series. Publications that Powell read in preparing these two speeches can be found in series "14.3.7 --Magna Carta."
  - Commission On Constitutional Revision (Virginia) 1968-1971
    Consists of two feet of papers and records concerning Powell's work as a member of this commission charged with the task of thoroughly revising the 35,000 word 1902 constitution. Included in this series are: general correspondence and memoranda; "public comment" correspondence and memoranda; memoranda from the Commission's executive director, A.E. Dick Howard (additional Howard correspondence concerning the Commission is in the general correspondence subseries of the Personal Papers subgroup); Powell's handwritten meeting notes; subcommittee files; drafts and text of the new constitution; and printed materials and clippings.
    The commission worked in subcommittees and Powell, and his fellow State Board of Education member, Colgate Darden, were assigned to the subcommittee on education. It is clear from inspecting these papers, however, that Powell had significant input in several other areas, most notably taxation. (Virginia's pressing need to be able to borrow money more easily was an important force behind undertaking the revision at that time.) In fact, there are few records about education in these papers and none specifically about the work of the education subcommittee. Powell and Darden's work can be seen in the drafts of the constitution in which the State Board of Education is given a greater role in setting standards, and in which cities and counties are required to keep their schools open.
    - Correspondence and Memoranda
      - General 1968-1971 (Box-folder 255/17-22, Box-folder 256/1-10)
      - Public Comment, 1968 (Box-folder 256/11-19)
    - Memoranda From Executive Director, 1968 (Box-folder 257/1)
    - Notes, 1968 & n.d. (Box-folder 257/2)
    - Resolution Creating Commission, 1968 (Box-folder 257/3)
    - Minutes, 1968 (Box-folder 257/4)
    - Subcommittees
      - Report, Subcommittee Tentative Questions, May 1968 (Box-folder 257/5)
      - Bill of Rights, July 1968 (Box-folder 257/6)
      - Executive and State Administration, 1968 (Box-folder 257/7-9, Box-folder 258/1)
      - Legislative and Judicial, July 1968 (Box-folder 258/2-4)
      - Local Government, July 1 1968 (Box-folder 258/5-7)
      - Taxation, July 1968
        - Correspondence, 1968 (Box-folder 258/8)
        - Notes, 1968 (Box-folder 258/9)
        - Memoranda
          - General, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 258/10-17)
          - Research Memoranda On State Debt, July 17, 1968 (Box-folder 259/1)
        - Working Papers, 1968 (Box-folder 259/2-5)
        - Preliminary Draft #1, October 3, 1968 (Box-folder 259/6)
        - Commentaries, 1968 (Box-folder 259/7)
        - Texts of Proposed Revisions, 1968 (Box-folder 259/8-9)
        - Senate and House Resolutions, 1968 (Box-folder 259/10)
    - Preliminary Draft Constitution, c. December 1968 (Box-folder 259/11, Box-folder 260/1-3)
      In four volumes.
    - Text of Proposed Revised Constitution, c. December 1968 (Box-folder 260/4)
    - Printed Materials, 1969 (Box-folder 260/5)
    - Clippings, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 260/6)
- Board Memberships 1937-1994
  The subgroup Board Memberships contains records and papers concerning many of the numerous civic, educational and corporate boards to which Powell belonged. Powell served as counsel--often pro bono or at reduced hourly fees--for many of the civic organizations of which he was a board member. He served as general counsel to several of the corporations whose boards he would later join. As a result, records of some actions taken by Powell as legal representative were interfiled with records of his board membership. As previously mentioned, all other files concerning clients represented by Powell are retained by Hunton & Williams. This subgroup, therefore, is at least as important for its documentation of Powell's lawyering as it is in recording his work as a board member. In addition to representing these firms in specific actions, in nearly every instance Powell was involved in revising basic organizational documents, especially charters and bylaws. He resigned from all corporate boards when his nomination to the Supreme Court was confirmed.
  - Civic 1940-1966
    Series 1. Civic, 1940-1966 is 4.5 cubic feet in extent and includes the subseries:
    8.1.1 Family Service Society, 1940-1957; c.2 in.
    8.1.2 Retreat for the Sick, 1941-1965; c. 3 in.
    8.1.3 Richmond Memorial Hospital, 1946-1966; 2 cu.ft.
    8.1.4 Gunston Hall, 1951-1965; .5 cu.ft.
    8.1.5 Virginia Home for Incurables, 1946-1964; 1 cu.ft.
    8.1.6 Richmond Area Community Chest/Fund, 1952-1957; 2 in.
    8.1.7 Society of Colonial Wars, 1958-1964; 1 in.
    8.1.8 Grace Covenant Presbyterian Church, 1961-1966; .5 in.
    Subseries "8.1.3 Richmond Memorial Hospital" is especially noteworthy as Powell was one of the incorporators of the hospital, in addition to serving as counsel and trustee. One of his most significant appellate cases involved the hospital. City of Richmond v. Richmond Memorial Hospital established the tax exempt status under Virginia law of community-type hospitals. This case is extensively documented in the papers.
    - Family Service Society, 1940-1957 (Box-folder 261/1-12)
    - Retreat For the Sick
      - Correspondence, 1941-1957 & 1965 (Box-folder 261/13-20)
      - Legal Papers, 1949-1957 (Box-folder 261/21)
      - Financial Statements, 1941-1950 (Box-folder 261/22)
      - Fund Raising, n.d. (Box-folder 261/23)
      - Minutes and By-Laws, 1939-1955 (Box-folder 261/24)
    - Richmond Memorial Hospital
      - Correspondence, 1946-1966 (Box-folder 261/25-33, Box-folder 262/1-16)
      - Subject Files
        - Applications to the State, 1947-1951 (Box-folder 262/17)
        - By-Laws for Medical Staff, 1956-1960 (Box-folder 262/18)
        - Certificate of Incorporation, 1947 (Box-folder 262/19)
        - Charter and By-Laws, 1947-1962 (Box-folder 262/20-22, Box-folder 263/1)
        - Contracts, 1950-1957 (Box-folder 263/2)
        - Forms, 1957-1962 (Box-folder 263/3)
        - Legal Memoranda, 1949-1956 (Box-folder 263/4)
        - Minutes, 1946-1961 (Box-folder 263/5)
        - Resolutions, 1948-1958 (Box-folder 263/6)
      - Case Files
        - Union Theological Seminary Lease
          - Correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 263/7)
          - Lease Agreement and Notes, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 263/8)
        - Laburnum Gift
          - Correspondence, 1950 (Box-folder 263/9)
          - Plat Map and Deed of Gift, 1950-1951 (Box-folder 263/10)
        - City Property Taxes
          - Correspondence, 1952-1963 (Box-folder 263/26)
          - Memoranda of Law, 1954-1959 (Box-folder 263/27, Box-folder 264/1-4)
          - Appeal and Motion to Dismiss Appeal, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 264/5)
          - Pleading, 1957-1960 (Box-folder 264/6-16)
          - Briefs, 1958-1960 (Box-folder 264/17-22, Box-folder 265/1-7)
          - Notes and Draft Documents, c. 1958-1960 (Box-folder 265/8)
          - Witnesses and Exhibits, 1949, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 265/9)
          - Mr. Bartley's Research Materials
            - Information from Other Hospitals, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 265/10)
            - Statistical Data, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 265/11)
            - Virginia Council on Uniform Hospital Accounting, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 265/12)
            - Free Service Accounts, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 265/13)
            - Contracts, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 265/14)
            - Rates, 1959 (Box-folder 265/15)
          - Printed Materials and Clippings, 1949, 1958 (Box-folder 266/1)
        - Adams v. White
          - Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 266/2-4)
          - Notes, n.d. (Box-folder 266/5)
          - Statements and Exhibits, 1961 (Box-folder 266/6)
          - Jury Instructions, n.d. (Box-folder 266/7)
          - Motions and Release, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 266/8)
        - Sheltering Arms Affiliation
          - Correspondence, 1961-1965 (Box-folder 266/9)
          - Notes, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 266/10)
          - Memoranda, 1962 (Box-folder 266/11)
          - Proposed Plan of Affiliation, 1961 (Box-folder 266/12)
          - Working Papers, 1962 (Box-folder 266/13)
          - Policies and Procedures, 1962 (Box-folder 266/14)
          - Drafts of Lease Agreement, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 266/15)
          - Lease Agreement, June 1962 (Box-folder 266/16)
    - Gunston Hall
      - Correspondence, 1951-1965 (Box-folder 266/17-21, Box-folder 267/1-3)
      - By-Laws, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 267/4)
      - Legal Documents, 1932-1961 (Box-folder 267/5)
      - Notes, 1951-1953 & n.d. (Box-folder 267/6)
    - Virginia Home For Incurables
      The name of this organization was changed to The Virginia Home in 1963.
      - Correspondence, 1939-1967 (Box-folder 267/7-34, Box-folder 268/1-4)
      - Subject Files
        - Charter and By-Laws, 1894, 1946-1963 (Box-folder 268/5)
        - Dewey v. Dewey, 1960 (Box-folder 268/6)
        - Exemption for Estate and Gift Taxes, 1948 (Box-folder 268/7)
        - Financial Statements, 1943-1949, 1960-1963 (Box-folder 268/8)
        - Forms and Policies, 1931, 1958-1963 (Box-folder 268/9)
        - Leases and Contracts, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 268/10)
        - Minutes and Reports, 1949, 1957 (Box-folder 268/11)
        - Legal Documents - Miscellaneous, 1946-1959 (Box-folder 268/12)
        - Notes, 1946-1961 & n.d. (Box-folder 268/13)
        - Pleadings, 1948-1958 (Box-folder 268/14)
        - Real Estate, 1946 (Box-folder 268/15)
        - Resolutions, 1946-1963 (Box-folder 268/16)
      - Estates
        - Bilek, Bertha
          - Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 268/17)
          - Court Papers, 1961-1964 (Box-folder 268/18)
        - Ferguson, Florence J., 1959-1960 (Box-folder 269/1)
        - Johnson, Lottie M.
          - Correspondence, 1960-1964 (Box-folder 269/2)
          - Court Papers, 1958-1961 (Box-folder 269/3)
        - Lumsden, George P., 1960 (Box-folder 269/4)
        - Harris, Laura J., 1960-1961 (Box-folder 269/5)
        - Hayes, John G., 1946 (Box-folder 269/6)
        - Matthews, Charles E.
          - Correspondence, 1958-1961 (Box-folder 269/7)
          - Court Papers, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 269/8)
        - Perkinson, Emma E.
          - Correspondence, 1946 (Box-folder 269/9)
          - Court Papers, 1946 (Box-folder 269/10)
        - Pollard, Fannie R., 1949 (Box-folder 269/11)
        - Simmons, Lucius C.
          - Correspondence, 1947-1948 (Box-folder 269/12)
          - Papers, 1947-1948 (Box-folder 269/13)
        - Swann, George, Jr.
          - Correspondence, 1949-1952 (Box-folder 269/14)
          - Court Papers, 1941-1952 (Box-folder 269/15)
        - Turpin, Allen, 1955-1960 (Box-folder 269/16)
        - Young, John F. and Marian C.
          - Correspondence, 1960 (Box-folder 269/17)
          - Court Papers, 195-1960 (Box-folder 269/18)
      - Printed Materials, 1948-c.1964 (Box-folder 269/19)
    - Richmond Area Community Chest/Fund
      - Correspondence, 1952-1957 (Box-folder 269/20)
      - Minutes and Notices, 1952 (Box-folder 269/21)
      - By-Laws, 1929, 1952-1953 (Box-folder 269/22)
      - Certificate of Incorporation, 1952-1957 (Box-folder 269/23)
      - Zincke Suit, 1956 (Box-folder 269/24)
    - Society of Colonial Wars
      - Correspondence, 1958-1964 (Box-folder 270/1-4)
      - Miscellaneous Papers, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 270/5)
    - Grace Covenant Presbyterian Church, 1961-1966 (Box-folder 270/6)
  - Educational 1937-1994
    Series 8.2. Educational includes 2 feet of papers, half of which composes subseries 8.2.1 Washington and Lee University, 1937-1994. Powell's long and devoted service to his alma mater is extensively documented here. Correspondence as a member of the Alumni Association of Richmond, from years before he joined the board, is also included here.
    Subseries 8.2.2 Washington School of Public Law, 1947-1949; 1 inch in extent, consists of correspondence concerning an unsuccessful attempt to launch a graduate school of public law in Washington, D.C. It was to have been a cooperative, experimental law school located within the Washington College of Law.
    Subseries 8.2.3 Union Theological Seminary, 1952-1968; is made up of two inches correspondence from Powell's service on that board. He served on the finance committee and gave legal and investment advice to that body.
    Subseries 8.2.4 Hollins College, 1956-1966; .25 cubic foot, consists of general correspondence and papers about the selection of a new president in 1960.
    - Washington and Lee University
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1934, 1941-1996 (Box-folder 270/7-34, Box-folder 271/1-29, Box-folder 272/1-23, Box-folder 273/8)
        - Alumni Association of Richmond, 1937-1941 (Box-folder 273/9)
        - Estate Planning Council, 1971 (Box-folder 273/10)
        - Henry Groop Fund, 1940-1941 (Box-folder 273/11)
        - Law Library Committee, 1958 (Box-folder 273/12)
        - Presidential Selection Committee, 1967 (Box-folder 273/13)
        - Rector Nominating Committee, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 273/14-15)
      - Notes
        - Notes For Speech to Lynchburg Alumni, March 2, 1966 (Box-folder 273/16)
        - (Box-folder 273/17)
      - Charter and By-Laws, c. 1920-1965 (Box-folder 273/18)
      - Minutes, c. 1961-1967 (Box-folder 273/19)
      - Lists of Board Members, 1961-1986 & n.d. (Box-folder 273/20)
      - Printed Materials, 1929-1963 (Box-folder 273/21)
    - Washington School of Public Law
      - Correspondence, 1947-1949 (Box-folder 274/1)
      - Reports, 1947-1948 (Box-folder 274/2)
    - Union Theological Seminary 1952-1968, Correspondence is the sole form of material. (Box-folder 274/3-13)
    - Hollins College, Correspondence is the sole form of material.
      - General Correspondence 1956-1968 (Box-folder 274/15-28)
      - Selection of President, 1960 (Box-folder 274/29)
      - Lists of Trustees, 1955-1965 (Box-folder 274/30)
  - Corporate 1946-1972
    Series 8.3 Corporate, 5 cubic feet, contains 13 subseries:
    8.3.1 Hollywood Cemetery Company, 1946-1964; c. 2 in.
    8.3.2 E. R. Squibb & Sons, 1946-1951; 1 cu.ft.
    8.3.3 Miller and Rhoads, Inc., 1949-1961; 1 folder
    8.3.4 Richmond Cold Storage, 1949, 1954-1961; .5 in.
    8.3.5 Commonwealth Natural Gas Corporation, 1952-1958; 1 in.
    8.3.6 Ethyl Corporation, 1953-1971; 1 cu. ft.
    8.3.7 Colonial Williamsburg Foundation, 1955-1993; 1 cu. ft.
    8.3.7 State Planters Bank, 1959-1962; .5 cu. ft.
    8.3.8 Lawyers Title Insurance, 1965-1971; 1 folder
    8.3.9 First Colony Life Insurance Company, 1967-1969; 1.5 in.
    8.3.10 Philip Morris, 1967-1971; .75 cu. ft.
    8.3.11 Richmond Corporation, 1967-1971; 1 folder
    8.3.12 Chesapeake & Potomac Telephone Company, 1968-1972; .25 cu.ft.
    - Hollywood Cemetery
      The Hollywood Cemetery correspondence and papers deal more with Powell's legal representation of the company than with his service on its board.
      - Correspondence, 1946-1964 (Box-folder 275/1-3)
      - Minutes, 1960 (Box-folder 275/4)
      - By-Laws and Charter, 1924-c. 1956 (Box-folder 275/5)
      - Financial Report, 1946 (Box-folder 275/6)
      - Holzhauer v. Hollywood, 1950-1952 (Box-folder 275/7)
      - Historical Sketch, 1893 (Box-folder 275/8)
    - E. R. Squibb & Sons
      Powell's association with the pharmaceutical firm, E. R. Squibb & Sons was based on his wartime friendship with Lowell Weicker who became Squibb's president after the war. The Squibb board papers consist primarily of correspondence, though memoranda, notes and minutes are also present.
      - Correspondence, 1946-1952 (Box-folder 275/9-36, Box-folder 276/1-5)
      - Christmas Lists, 1946-1951 (Box-folder 276/6)
      - Memoranda, 1946-1949 (Box-folder 276/7)
      - Notes, 1952 & n.d. (Box-folder 276/8)
      - By-Laws and Organizational Charts, 1946-1952 (Box-folder 276/9)
      - Minutes, 1946-1952 (Box-folder 276/10-14, Box-folder 277/1-2)
      - Securities and Exchange Commission Form S-1, 1945 (Box-folder 277/3)
    - Miller and Rhoads, Inc., 1949-1961 (Box-folder 277/4)
      The Miller and Rhoads, Richmond Cold Storage and Commonwealth Natural Gas board papers are small in size and unexceptional in content. There is a long run of board minutes with the Commonwealth Natural Gas papers.
    - Richmond Cold Storage
      - Correspondence, 1949 (Box-folder 277/5)
      - Minutes, 1954-1961 (Box-folder 277/6)
    - Commonwealth Gas Corporation
      - Correspondence, 1952-1962 (Box-folder 277/7-8)
      - Memoranda, 1952-1954 (Box-folder 277/9)
      - Minutes, 1952-1962 (Box-folder 277/10-14)
      - Annual Report, 1952 (Box-folder 277/15)
    - Ethyl Corporation
      The subseries 8.3.6 Ethyl Corporation contains: correspondence and memoranda; memoranda of law on a variety of topics; basic corporation papers (by-laws, charter, articles of incorporation, merger and reduction, certificates of filing, etc.); financial statements; minutes; contracts; litigation papers; and printed materials.
      Perhaps most interesting is the record volume entitled "Working Documents [re] Acquisition by Albemarle Paper Company." Albemarle Paper Company became a Powell client in 1950. In 1962 Albemarle's president, Floyd Gottwald, entered into negotiations to purchase the much larger Ethyl Corporation. In what is considered to be one of the first corporate leveraged buy outs, Powell's team of attorneys completed the merger on November 30, 1962. The newly combined company took the name Ethyl Corporation.
      - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1953-1992 (Box-folder 278/1-6)
      - Memoranda of Law
        - General, 1953-1958 & n.d. (Box-folder 278/7)
        - Garnishment, 1954-1959 (Box-folder 278/8)
        - A Survey of Tax Laws Affecting the Albemarle Family, December 22, 1960 (Box-folder 278/9)
        - Conflicts of Interest, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 278/10)
        - Foreign Acquisition, 1963 (Box-folder 278/11)
        - Proposed Virginia Trade Secret Legislation, 1966 (Box-folder 278/12)
        - Controlling Persons, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 278/13)
        - Mergers and Charter Amendments, February 1, 1967 (Box-folder 278/14)
      - Record Volume: Ethyl Corporation Working Documents re Acquisition by Albemarle Paper Manufacturing Corporation, 1962 (Box-folder 278/15-16)
      - Articles of Incorporation, 1959-1967, 1968 (Box-folder 278/17)
      - Articles of Merger, 1962, 1968 (Box-folder 278/18)
      - Articles of Reduction, 1953-1967 (Box-folder 278/19)
      - By-Laws, 1962-1969 (Box-folder 279/1)
      - Certificates of Filing, 1962-1967 (Box-folder 279/2)
      - Financial Statements, 1953, 1955 & 1965 (Box-folder 279/3)
      - Minutes, 1957-1964 (Box-folder 279/4)
      - Contracts
        - General, 1951-1957, 1964 (Box-folder 279/5-6)
        - City of Richmond, 1959-1961 (Box-folder 279/7)
        - Rust Engineering Company, 1950, 1958 (Box-folder 279/8)
        - Southern Printing Ink Corporation, 1955-1957 (Box-folder 279/9)